<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The history of Valentine and Orson]</title>
            <title>Valentin et Orson. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1510</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24571.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110323</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845886</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845886</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10816</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14256)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10816)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1673:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[The history of Valentine and Orson]</title>
                  <title>Valentin et Orson. English.</title>
                  <author>Watson, Henry, fl. 1500-1518.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4+] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1510]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Henry Watson, of: Valentin et Orson.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from, and publication date and format conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>"Text of chap. 4 begins on B5r: Whan the Archebysshop .."--STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; consists of leaves B3-6 only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="fragment_of_The_History_of_Valentine_and_Orson">
            <pb facs="tcp:10816:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10816:2"/>wyfe / but cruelly and fyerſly anſwere vnto her. Falſe ſtrompet dyſhordynate of as moche as thou arte with chylde I ought lytell to reioyſe me / for I am ſo moche enformed of thy gouernement y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue nothyng / and that dyſloyally thou haſte habandoned thyſelfe vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than me. Whan they ſawe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de not refrayne hym nor appeſe his Ire for nothynge / by a comyn accorde they toke her and ledde her in to a chambre. And the mooſt amyably that they myght hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de her with wordes in ſhewy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vnto her her grete fau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / and the ſorowful lady was dyſorned in the chambre that hadde her face dyſteyned with bloode. The ladyes that were next her perſone brought her fayre water to waſſhe her withall. And at that houre entred in to her chambre her ſquyer named Blandymayn. And whan he ſawe her in ſuche eſtate / he wepte for pyte / and ſayd vnto her. Ha madame I ſe well that you are falſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed. I beſeche god that curſed be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſone that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the purchaſed you this euyll. For god my ryght dere la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy take a lytell comforte vnto you. And yf you wyll by leue me I ſhall lede you in to Fraunce agayne towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the kynge Pepyn your broder / the whiche gaue me vnto you for to ſerue you in your neceſſytees / the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thynge I wolde do after my puyſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Byleue my counſayll and we ſhall retorne in to Fraunce agayne. / For you maye be ſure that the Emperoure ſhall make you dye ſhortly with grete ſhame and diſhonour. Then anſwered the dolorous lady. Ha Blandymain my fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de it ſholde be to me to ſhamefull and dyſhoneſt for to go in ſuche maner without other delyberacyon. And it myght be byleued lyghtly that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour had goode cauſe / and that I were culpable of the dede. Wherfore
<pb facs="tcp:10816:3"/>
I had leuer deye an euyll dethe / than for to recouer bla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me for a thynge that I am innocent of / &amp; accuſed with out cauſe. After theſe thynges thus ſayd / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour that was with the barons a lytell moderate and ſatyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed of his Ire / he ſente for his wyfe Bellyſſant / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che was brought before hym quyckely. Whan he ſawe her his herte trembled for ſorowe for this that he durſt not put her to dethe / bycauſe of her broder kynge Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyn / and his puyſſaunce. With tude wordes he ſayd to her. Falſe and curſed woman by the is myn honour vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turped Wherfore I ſwere god that and it were not for thy broders ſake / the valyaunt kynge Pepyn / I ſholde make the to be brente in a fyre / out for his ſake thy lyfe ſhall be prolonged at this preſent tyme. Now I do the to wyte that from this houre I banyſſhe the / &amp; expulſe the from my countree and Empyre / in commaundyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the expreſly that to morowe thou departe out of this cyte / for yf I ſe the ony more / thou ſhall neuer haue reſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyte tyll thou haue ſuffred dethe. And yet I commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de all them of my countre / that there be none ſo hardy of them to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany you / or conueye / ſaue alonely your ſquyer Blandymayn that you brought out of Fraunce with you. Go where as you wyll goo at your auenture / for thou ſhall neuer ſlepe by my ſyde / nor in my bedde / Soone after the commaundement of the Emperoure that was ſhorte and ſodayne / without ſoiourne or dela<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon / the Empreſſe Bellyſſant / and her ſquyer Blandy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mayn mounted on horſbacke and came in to the Cyte. Where as was ſhedde ful many a tere / bothe of lordes and ladyes / knyghtes / and ſquyers / with all the comin people / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche cryed and ſorowed out of meſure / for they made ſuche lamentacyons that there was neuer
<pb facs="tcp:10816:3"/>
ſene / nor herde ſo pyteous a thynge. Euery body ranne vnto the gate / for to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde the good lady vnto god that by the falſe Archebyſſhoppe was ſo pyteouſly ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed. And at the yſſue of the gate they made the py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefulleſt crye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer was herde. Nowe gothe Blandy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayn that conduyteth the ſorowfull lady Bellyſſant / And hathe taken the way to go towarde the realme of Fraunce. Whan the lady was oute of the walles of the cyte / and that ſhe ſawe herſelfe in the feldes pyteouſly aourned / lyke a woman ſhamed and dyſhonoured / ſhe wayled bytterly. For ſhe conſydered the lygnage / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloode ryall that ſhe was yſſued out of / the ryght hyghe magnyfycence imperyall that ſhe had ben put in. And after thought on the myſerable and dolorous fortune y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was torned vpon her ſo ſodaynly / ſhe ſayd. Alas alas wherfore taryeth dethe that he wyll not come &amp; abred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge my lyfe / and fyniſſhe my dolours and anguyſſhes / Alas I was borne in an vnhappy houre for to ſuffre ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che payne / and for to fall from ſo hye eſtate vnto ſuche pouerte / for of all the vnhappyes I am the mooſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happyeſt. Now is al my ioyes tranſmued in to dyſtres my laughynges chaunged in to wepynges / my ſonges conuerted in to ſyghes. In the ſtede of the clothe of gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that I was wonte for to were / I am as a woman publyke ful of iniuryes and vytupere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted &amp; aour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned. And of precyous ſtones of ineſtymable valour / on all ſydes I muſt the remenaunt of my myſerable lyfe arouſe my veſture with bytter teeres / that ſhall make my lyfe and my dayes to fynyſſhe. O you paſtorelles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feldes conſyder my grete dolours / and wepe myn exyle. Now pleaſed it god and the vyrgyn Mary that I were deſcended of as poore eſtate as the pooreſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10816:4"/>
worlde / at the leeſt I ſholde haue doloure to ſe me in ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che pouerte. Alas wherfore lyghteth me the ſonne / and wherfore dothe the erthe ſuſteyne me / for I haue no ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de that the daungerous fountayne of dyſtreſſe oppreſſe me ſo ſore. For it is not in myne humayne puyſſaunce / to bewayle the profounde ſorowe that my poore herte endureth. O falſe enuye and treaſon / I ought well for to curſe the with my herte / for by the to daye I am the mooſt ſorowfulleſt creature lyuynge vpon the erthe. A my broder the kynge Pepyn / what ſhal ye do with this poore dyſcomforted. It were better for you that I had neuer ben borne of my moder / or that from the wombe of my moder I hadde ben put vnder the erthe. In ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge this aſpre complaynt the lady abode in a ſwow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vpon the horſbacke / &amp; ſhe was almooſt fallen dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne or that Blandymayn myght come vnto her / then he dreſſed her vp and ſayd vnto her. Alas madame take vnto you ſome comforte / and entre not ſo in to dyſpay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re / haue ſtedfaſt truſte in god / for euen ſoo as you are innocente he ſhall kepe you and defende you alwayes / Then he eſpyed a ryght fayre fountayne / towarde the whiche he ledde the lady. And alſo nere it as he myght he ſet her downe for to repoſe her and refreſſhe her. He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re I wyll leue to ſpeke of them / and wyll ſpeke of the Archebyſſhop that perſeuered in his malyce dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and dyabolyke.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶How the Archebyſſhop put hym in the habyte of a knyght / and mounted on horſbacke for to folowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Empreſſe Bellyſſant y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was banyſſhed. Ca. iiij.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10816:4"/>
                  <figure>
                     <p>Archebyſ.</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>WHan the Archebyſſhop ſawe that the lady was departed / he thought in hymſelfe that he wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de go after her / and that with her he wolde do his pleaſure. He lefte rochet and other veſture / and as irreguler and apoſtate / gyrde his ſwerde aboute hym / and mounted vpon a ſwyfte courſer / and folowed faſt after / for he had one of the beſt courſer of all Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynoble. He rode ſo faſte that within ſhort tyme he had ryden a grete waye. And of all them that he mette he aſked tydynges of the noble lady Bellyſſant. And they ſhewed vnto hym the waye that ſhe helde. So longe ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the falſe traytour Archebyſſhoppe that he entred in
<pb facs="tcp:10816:5"/>
to a myghty grete foreſt and a longe / he toke the hyghe waye and enforced hym to ryde a paas. He had not ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den longe whan he apperceyued the lady with Blandy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mayn / the whiche were beſyde the fountayne where as the lady was diſcended for to refreſſhe her / and reſt her for ſhe was wery and heuy full of ſorowe and doloure / ſo that ſhe myght not ſuſteyne her. Whyles that Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dymayn comforted the ſorowfull lady / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Archebyſſhop drewe nere them / and knewe the fayre Bellyſſant / but ſhe knewe hym not a ferre bycauſe that he was dyſgy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed / but whan he approched ſhe knewe hym well ynou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe. Alas ſayd ſhe Blandymayn / I ſe nowe come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde vs the falſe Archebyſſhop that is cauſe of myn exyle. Alas I am to ſore aferde that he do me not ſome vyllanye. Lady ſayd Blandymayn / haue of hym ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fere nor doubte. For yf he come for to doo you euyl or diſpleaſure I ſhal put my body for to defende yours vnto the dethe. At theſe wordes was arryued the arche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byſſhop that lyght of his hors / and ſalued the lady in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt maner that he myght and ſayd. Ryght dere and ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noured lady / yf ſo be that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour hathe dechaced you / yf you wyll accepte me for to be your loue / and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complyſſhe my deſyre / I ſhall do ſo moche towarde the Emperour that he ſhall put you in your fyrſte eſtate / &amp; be exalted more hygher than euer you were / wherfore auyſe you / for I do it for your grete honoure and prouf fyte. Ha ſayd the lady / dyſloyall and cruell aduerſary of all honoure imperyall / I ought well to haue cauſe to lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the / and holde the dere / whan that by thy falſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce thou haſte made the Emperour vnderſtonde that I haue myſerably borne me towarde his maieſte / and made me be deiecte from all honoure and proſperyte. /
<pb facs="tcp:10816:5"/>
Thou haſt put me in the waye of extremyte and myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye / and is the cauſer that I ſhal fynyſſhe my dayes in dolorous dyſtreſſe / for there is not a more dyſcomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lady in the worlde than I am. Lady leue ſuche wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des / for by me there can nothyng come to you but good For I am puyſſaunt ynoughe for to chaunge your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loure and dyſcomforte in to Ioye &amp; ſolace / more than euer you had. In ſayenge theſe wordes he enclyned hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towarde the lady / and wende to haue kyſſed her. But Blandymayn ſterte bytwene them and gaue the Arche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byſſhop ſo grete a ſtroke that he felled hym vnto the er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the / and brake twayne of his tethe. The Archebyſſhop gate hym vp and drewe his ſwerde quyckly. And Blan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dymayn toke a glayue that he had broughte with hym and aſſaylled hym ryght aſprely / and the Archebiſſhop hym. They fought ſoo longe that they were bothe ſore wounded. And as they were thus fyghtynge / there ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryued on them a notable marchaunt / that aſcryed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them alſo ferre as he myght ſe them ſaynge. Lordes lordes leue your debate / and tell me fro whens it proce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth / &amp; I ſhall tell you who hathe ryght or wronge. ſyr ſayd Bla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dymayn let vs fynyſſhe our enterpryſe. Alas ſayd the lady ſocoure vs / for here is the fals preeſt that wyll take myn honour from me by force / whiche is the curſed Archebyſſhop / that hathe ſepared me by treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from my lorde and huſbande the Emperoure. Whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> marchaunt vnderſtode her / he had grete pyte on her / &amp; ſayd to the Archebyſſhop. Syr leue your enterpryſe / &amp; touche not the lady / for and the Emperoure knewe of this dede / he wolde make you deye an euyll dethe before all the worlde. Alſo ſoone as the Archebiſſhoppe vnder ſtode the marchaunt ſpeke / he lefte the batayll quyckly
<pb facs="tcp:10816:6"/>
and began for to fle thorughe the wodde. He was ryght ſorowfull that he was knowen / for he thoughte well to haue had his pleaſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lady. But he enterpryſed ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che a thynge / wherby his treaſon was knowen after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde / and dyſcloſed as it ſhall be recounted to you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde. After the departynge of the Archebyſſhop y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lady abode in the wodde beſyde the fountayne tryſte &amp; ſorowfull / with Blandymayne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was wounded. The marchaunt that was abyden ſayd. Alas lady I ſe that by the Archebiſſhop ye are falſly betrayed / and haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expulſed from the Emperoure. Now god gyue me gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce to lyue ſo longe that I maye accuſe hym of this myſ dede / and to purchaſe his dethe. Lady to god I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde you the whiche gyue you pacyence &amp; comforte Soo the marchaunte toke his leue / and Blandymayn thanked hym many tymes. Then Blandymayn moun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted the lady vpon her hors / and after mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vpon his owne / and wente vnto a lodgynge that was there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde / where as they abode by the ſpace of .viij. days for to hele Blandymayn. Whan he had reſted hym / &amp; that he myght ryde they put them vpon the waye towarde Fraunce. And the ſorowfull lady complayned her by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye and ſayd. Alas Blandymayn my frende / what may my broder &amp; all the lordes ſaye of my pyteous ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe / whan they ſhall knowe that for a vyllaynous dede I am ſo ſhamefully deiecte from the Emperoure / and as a comon woman banyſſhed the Empyre of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynoble. Alas I am ryght certayne that my broder wyl byleue lyghtly that I am culpable of the dede / &amp; make me dye ſhamefully / for he is ryght fyerſe of courage / la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy ſayd blandymayn be of good chere / &amp; put your truſt in god. In ſpekynge thus Blandymayn that the lady
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10816:6"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
